[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software this is Adam Conrad for
software engineering radio epan has
worked on distributed platforms for
internet applications for over 11 years
he started at Yahoo on Yahoo's nosql
database project leading the development
of multiple features such as real-time
notification of database updates
secondary indexes and live migration
from Legacy systems to nosql databases
he joined and led the distributed Cloud
messaging system project later which is
used heavily as a pub sub and
transaction log for distributed
databases in Yahoo from 2014 he joined
LinkedIn and has quickly become the lead
of the samza team in LinkedIn and a
committer and PMC member
in Apache samza e thanks for coming on
to software engineering radio thanks
thanks Adam for introducing all right so
let's get started with samza so sza
actually uh is a uh stream processing
platform uh building LinkedIn so uh
before we get into the you know more
detailed introduction about the S itself
let's first you know introduce the
concept of stream processing so uh
stream processing start at you know data
processing in a big data area starts
from the map reduce Hado and hdfs which
process a large size of the uh data in
batches the technology is optimized for
throughput not latency so usually people
needs to wait for hours or days to get
that antical result from the batch shops
however the emerging needs in the
dynamic interaction with the user in
session uh for internet applications
demands faster iteration and shorter
latency in getting the analytical
results from the Real Time data this
requires us to process the events as
they come in and general result to serve
Online requests in minutes or seconds
which we call stream processing that's
the uh the particular domain that s of
technology is build in right so s as one
of those stream processing platform it
started in 2011 uh sorry 2013 late 2013
in LinkedIn right after kafa became
widely adopted in LinkedIn the first
application that motivate the whole idea
is an internal application that tracks
the call Tree in linkedin's microservice
Stacks uh we want to get all the
invocations of microservices according
to a single user request received from
the front end and then being able to
join them all together to uh build a COR
graph tree to understand okay how much
time that uh you know how many calls
each of the user requests will F out to
how much uh time we spend in each of
these uh micro microservice Stacks from
the Inception then we have built the
platform with the following concepts a
uh it is tily integrated with cfal for
high performance B it is hosted
execution uh platform to support multi
tendency and C this platform needs to
support high throughput and short
latency State Stores to support stateful
stream processing with at least one
semantics so this sounds quite a quite a
lot requirements to achieve all the
above then uh sza actually is designed
with uh the following techniques to
address each of them so we have created
an advanced wrapper of the io connector
on Kafka to achieve per partition thr
control when consuming many topic
partitions for a single consumer
instance so we were able to achieve a
sing using a single consumer instance
who consume tens or even hundreds of a
topic predictions paralyze processing on
all of them um and having a very fine
granular thr control for each of the top
petitions so one of the top one of the
threat becomes slow for one of the topic
petitions will not affect the others the
the other to address the you know uh to
provide a hosted execution platform for
multi tendency Works uh we integral with
the yarn as the hosted execution
platform to manage hardware and also the
container execution for the user
application that way then user won't
need to manage their own uh the user
will not will not need to manage their
own Hardware will not need to manage
their own Monitor and manage their own
process liveness and yarn is leveraged
as the distributed and hosted execution
platform to run the uh us applications
third to achieve the high super and shot
latency for the state stores we also
Implement a unique architecture using
Kafka as the right ahead log and then
Rock DB as the local state stores for
sard containers that allows us to
achieve really high throughput and low
leny when we are rewrite the state
stores which is a effectively at Rock TV
uh database so in addition Sor also
leverages kka as intermediate shuffling
cues between stages in the Stream
processing pipeline to achieve the
repetion with for uh with a f uh with f
and failure isolation lately we have
advanced sensors apis a lot as well to
add SQL to add beam Runner and multi
language support on top of beam
especially python to allow easier usage
and support Reacher window semantics
where the beam apis so that hopefully
give a overall view of what sza is and
then um how some details about how sza
is implemented yes that is a very
thorough introduction so I would love to
take a higher view Let's uh pull it back
to maybe a 20,000 foot view stream
processing and General uh what
constitutes big data in 2020 are we
talking terabytes of data pedabytes of
data where does one start when they're
looking at stream processing so that
depends on whether we are looking at the
whole Collective uh of all the stream
process pipelines in a company or we're
looking at a single one as for today
like in as a whole we are processing at
the north of like 3 to 5 million events
per second as a whole collector in the
cluster as a as a whole and then in some
of the individual jobs the large jobs
can process itself process close to 1
million messages per second and then uh
having a state store close to uh 10 10
terabytes and growing and why would I
need to process streams of data what
what kinds of use cases are people
finding for stream processing stream
processing usually is as as I explained
earlier that is usually applied to the
cases that you want a faster interaction
to faster interaction and the shorter
Laten to get an etical result for
example in a session when user open a
website and start to read some articles
or click on some interesting content
then those user activities will be sent
back in real time to the backend uh
serving system and usually in the
session itself within seconds or minutes
the platform needs to understand okay
what is the current user intention and
based on that to supply Dynamic contents
like further recommendations of more
interesting contents or some
advertisement pertaining to the uh to
the user interest for example the user
is looking at some uh job market stuff
then probably he's interested in a
relevant like job posting so these kind
of uh um interactions uh you cannot
suffer from latency that okay say oh I
have this tracking uh user track
activities sent back to my hadu cluster
and wait for 4 hours and you know
getting you know uh get back the result
to the user by that time the user is
already gone so anytime I see a
recommendation engine where it's
recommending me something else to watch
or listen to there's likely stream
processing going on underneath to ensure
that that returns quickly yes correct
and so then when should I not consider
using a stream processing framework to
handle my data so stream processing
definitely favors latency versus
throughput and because of that it
consumes a lot of uh resources to um
store and keep the intermediate result
in the uh and partial and intermediate
result in the system so and rs 24/7 so
if your analytical result does not
really impact in session Dynamic
engagement with user then you can save a
lot by doing a batch process which
dynamically allocates tons of a uh tons
of a res resources and then shrink it
down and wrap it up once it's done so uh
that's a trade that's a trade-off
between running a stream process which
is uh you know long running forever
antical results anal uh frow versus a
batch based basically okay once the data
is there you can schedule a massive
parallelism just to turn through the
data all uh you know as fast as you can
and then stop then release all the
resources to the system back and is
there a pivot point where batching just
doesn't work and it makes more sense to
to switch to a stream processing
framework because I think a lot of
companies batching is definitely one of
the first ways that they think about
scaling correct uh the data that they're
ingesting and so is there a is there a
signal that people can look for when
they say Okay batching just isn't
working and there there's something I
might want to consider in advance before
they start looking at stream processing
Frameworks so uh I think there's no like
hard set rules for okay when you should
switch to stream processing but
definitely there are some lure some like
if it because if you start a if the
batch process you start uh to have a
shorter shorter Cadence then the batch
process needs to have a more uh you know
heavier load on the scheduler saying
okay instead of every hour you scheduled
once now every hour you need to schedule
it four times for for example like every
every 15 minutes you need to you need to
schedule something then it is uh it is
into the boundary of the area that okay
if that's the case why don't you just
schedule once for 20 uh 24/7 and then
you know allocate the resources there
because even in that area if you if
you're running the 15 minute window
batch process and then each of the batch
processing also takes foro 40 minutes to
finish then literally you're not saving
any resource uh in in terms of like a
batch bursting mode that that you can
use the resource and release anymore
because now you're sort of like a
continuously using that amount of
resource then in that sense then why
don't you uh the the the uh sentiment
here is okay now with more and more
scheduled short latency biry batch jobs
you actually are continuously using
those resources anyways and you're
paying the cost of ramping up and
ramping down why not just let it let it
wrong all the time great and for more
information on General streaming
architectures you should check out
episode 346 where we go into that in
more detail so that's a that's a good
overview in choosing those Frameworks um
and you did a really great job of
explaining samza at a very high level so
talking more about those internals I'd
like to dive into each of those three
parts of the core architecture so we've
got the streaming provided by Kafka
we've got the execution provided by yarn
and the the processing itself done by
the samza API so first I'd like to start
with the streaming from Kafka so are
these two projects developed together uh
very closely so sza as I as I explained
a little bit earlier so Sansa started
right after Kafka became widely adopted
in LinkedIn and it was developed by even
the the co-founder of the project is
also some uh you know uh heavily
influenced by Kafka and even J crops is
also the co-creator of Sor project
so it it's literally just a sister team
in LinkedIn with Ka and so are they
required to work together like do you
have to have Kafka in order to be able
to use samza uh not necessarily so sza
has all this uh although sza is a Cod
developer almost a Cod developer by a
Kafka and the leverages a lot of uh uh
its architecture choices you know the
implementation level use kfka a lot but
all the interfaces are plugable so you
can um for for sza you can plug in any
systems pops up systems with uh with sza
as long as you implement the system
interface uh system producer system
consumer interface then it will work
example would be uh we implemented
integration of sza with event hubs and
kesis those are those are all working
okay so there are examples of swapping
out Frameworks with Kafka for a
different one yes okay okay and then is
it just the fact that samza came shortly
after Kafka that they said well we since
we have to use streaming as a as a core
service for this group we might as well
leverage Kafka already since it's part
of the same organization and it's
already part of the aache umbrella
that's definitely one of the aspiration
but at a time that it you know uh as for
a large distributed pops up system uh
Kafka at that time is one of those
literally just one or two choices there
out there for open source so right now
samza is leveraging Kafka externally it
is its own sort of pluggable service as
you mentioned is there a plan where
samung can come prepackaged with some
dedicated streaming layer as part of the
samza project or will it always forever
have some sort of plug to a different
streaming layer oh uh it the current
implementation already have kesis and
event Hub implemented and the package it
together Al so I guess my question is
those are all external solutions from
different companies or different
projects right is there an is there an
idea to have Kafka be replaced by
something that is internal to samza so
samza owns the streaming layer got it so
um there's no intention to replace Kafka
as an internal layer but uh we made it
arure to be open that's the that's the
uh that's a concept okay so this was a
decided choice to ensure maximum
pluggability and modularity across
multiple systems got it okay and then
yarn a yarn execution layer is that
meant to stay with just yarn no there's
a definitely extension to that we spend
quite a bit of energy to uh move from a
very tight integration with the yarn
basically Sor cannot run without yarn to
a mode that the Senter can run with yarn
or uh you can run a standard s up and uh
we have some experim uh the you know uh
I think in the in the recent one year or
two we already have some experiment uh
Department with uh you know try to run s
on top of kubernetes as well and then
that's definitely ongoing like we will
have integr with more of advanced uh
state of art uh distributed execution
environment okay now is this the same
yarn I think of I come from a frontend
background I do a lot of web development
is this the same yarn that we use yarn
package management or is this a a
different yarn system oh that is Apache
yarn which is uh part of the Hado
ecosystem there's a res you know uh it's
a the resource man uh resource
management system that if you submit a
job asking for a set of resource to run
a set of a process it identifies the um
the physical host to run the containers
for you and the manager the likeness of
that right and so in general for folks
uh this is not the yarn you're thinking
of in the mpm system this is about like
you said resource management job
scheduling job execution it's ensuring
that those jobs that get input through
through the streaming uh process data
get executed appropriately exactly right
so when I was looking at the
architecture I noticed that Hadoop does
many of these same things as well and it
also seems to be the only service that
you share was this intentional to share
uh Hadoop as that execution Service uh
Hadoop mean you mean specifically uh
yarn right so correct yeah so uh yeah
just to clarify uh Hado is a big
ecosystem uh yarn is just part of the
project doing the resource uh scheduling
and we only leverage that part the and
and also as I explained sza uh leverages
yarn to U do the uh coordination among
all the processors in the same job to
have a single Master to uh allocate and
assign all the works among all the
worker all the processes and then
maintain the liveness and the membership
of these group but it's not necessarily
the only implementation the standard s
implementation actually replace that
model with zuk based coordination which
allows a set of processes basically
doing the leader election to uh lead
their Le uh lead their uh single leader
for the whole uh for the whole quarum
and then do the same uh resour do the
same like a workload balancing and
assignments among all the alive workers
as if there you know indic case that you
don't have a yarn okay yes that's what I
was going to ask you mentioned a
standalone samza so that means just like
Kafka you could also plug in a different
job scheduler as well outside of yarn
yes so I'm guessing the theme Here is
that in order to quickly accelerate and
this may just be a guess but in order to
quickly accelerate the development of
samza in the beginning it was so much
easier to leverage Kafka or yarn because
they were already part of the Apache
ecosystem than to have to build them out
yourself correct yeah got it but the
streaming or the actual processing part
of the application is done through the
samza API so I'm guessing when we look
at the entire sort of Three core system
the samza API itself is the most core
and Central to this
actual samza app project right right
this is the area that has the most
unique code compared to the other layers
yeah so uh one you know API depend on
well in my mind then when we talk about
swi processing apis in this case then it
will involve not only uh the io wrapper
that IO connector that read right front
the pop subsystem and also like um
should include the job checkpoint system
the uh State you know the state store
system as as well because in stream
processing without the checkpointing and
without the state store management
system you cannot really achieve
the you know failure recovery and
starting from you know and achieve the
at least ones and even exact ones
semantics without checkpointing or State
Management right and so when we think
about the entire project this was
actually one part that was confusing for
me was what do I actually call samza is
samza the entirety of Kafka plus yarn
and the samza API or is samza just the
API part to the whole stream processing
architecture Sansa actually builds a uh
builds a platform or framework to highs
all the system level Integrations with
IO uh with the pops up IO system with
the uh scheduling system and with the
state Source system in a set of apis
going around it and then allows user
basically allows user to plug in their
user logic in the event Loop you know
exposed through this API right so the
stitching layer happens all seamlessly
through the API and then there's a
subset of that API that is then revealed
to the consumer who actually wants to
handle that data data and send it
through either you know a container or
some sort of job to to schedule that for
later yes that's right yep and so that's
actually a good transition point when I
started looking at the Sam's API
essentially everything seems to be
either a job or some sort of container
so I'm very curious to see how how this
integrates into databases so when we
think of databases there are things like
acid guarantees like atomicity
consistency isolation durability are
there those kinds of guarantees in a
system like in a stream processing
framework so stream processing in terms
of like the St you know I take it as
okay the uh if you're comparing the
state uh St uh you know kind of a
student processing system with a
database then there's a famous like a
stream to table Duality blocks that uh a
few I think a few years ago um jcbs
posted there right so in streaming then
it is always view the table or database
as everchanging thing right and then
there's a uh if you're think about acid
control um usually it is not in the uh
synchronous uh you know uh it's not
guaranteed in a synchronous way right
most of this consistency guarantee is
based on the eventual consistency or you
can replace the same sequence and and
achieve the ADM pocy as a final result
yeah and actually you saying that makes
a ton of sense if this data is
constantly changing there would in in
essence there is no sense of consistency
ever because it's constantly changing
but like you said I think the eventual
consistency right is the right thing
there because at some point the job will
end that you've scheduled and you
expecting something to look like some
kind of result at the end of that job
but right in while it's processing it's
going to be consistently changing so
that makes sense from a from a
consistency standpoint are the jobs
themselves Atomic could you run them
again and again and again and get the
expect sort of the the action to
complete yeah so Atomic Atomic is also a
a strong word that is I think only
applicable to a single host or single um
you know kind of a CPU and centralized
Locking System with stream processing uh
with a sensor as a distributed stream
processing platform like as you know
designed from beginning Atomic is not
the design principle the design
principle is cons a consistency and also
B is the failure recovery with replay
with the replayable admony so what the
difference is okay in atomicity
basically you have few operations and as
you said you have a job you want to uh
the job has 10 different uh uh 10
different workers right and uh each of
them are doing something and you have to
say okay all the 10 processes finish one
operation in atomicity and then close
synchronize lock and then proceed right
in the eventual in the in the way that
uh eventual consistency and the
distributed um you know item bony works
is okay for each of these 10 process you
can proceed as your own pace but you
keep the state saying okay when you fail
or when you shut down the process saying
okay oh I remember process one is at
step uh three and process two is at step
uh one and then you have a vector of all
those states of the whole uh set of
processes there once you restore the
whole process uh the checkpoint May
always be at Step Zero for all the 10
process then um when the input are
replayed the all this processor will
need to check with their own States and
say oh this step I it's already
implemented and it's already applied uh
from the previous run for me I will skip
as a no op and then up up to the point
that okay this is Step that I have not
exed in the previous run and I continue
right so so then uh that's the that's
the way that you achieve a replay
consistency and item pocy in the D
system right okay and then so that
really doesn't make sense then to think
about it in terms of atomic because like
you said these aren't short running jobs
these could run for several hours or
several days or just they continuously
run and so let me just clarify a little
bit on that as well so atomicity okay
here if you want to apply atomicity you
can still do that by a centralized
Locking System say you apply a uh
barrier a centralized barrier through
zookeeper or something like that but but
that greatly affects the throughput and
a lot of a lot of those um stream
processing applications does not really
you know work well in the in the case of
you you have to keep up with thousands
of or millions of incoming messages as
input right so it almost defeats the
purpose then like you could technically
do it the logging itself almost acts
like a ledger then so you could like you
said if if the service gets interrupted
or it goes down for a bit of time The
Ledger is acting sort of like the state
machine which says
here's the state at a given time when
the servic is back up resume at this
line correct at this given State yeah
but all that extra logging is going to
affect throughput and so you almost
don't like you're saying there if you
needed those kind of requirements for
that data you probably wouldn't even be
doing stream processing in the first
place yeah exactly right that makes
sense okay so that covers I think the
the job aspect for
containers essentially it says that you
can excute arbitrary code so does that
mean that security is forced enforced by
the customer or is it expected by the
customer how does security handle for
these containers which could execute
anything right so that's a good point so
I think for uh sza applications the uh
the word arbitrary is also like slightly
misleading so it is it is just referring
to okay there's a hey there's a set of
java API and then with you know just
using this set of uh uh system provide
apis then you can do whatever you want
as implementing your user logic so if
the security is in the aspect of okay
saying are you able to in the regular
not really doing any hacky way in uh are
you able to get beneath the API layer to
get down to the system level resources
and objects uh then the security is
there yes uh there's no exposure of The
Underneath
system objects to the user except for
okay there's a message comes in message
is there if you want to use a state
store the state store API is there right
and if you want to input output you know
if you want to write to the uh any
system the producer API is there that's
the uh level of security that is there
but if you're talking about the user
want uh just in their code I sure write
some ref you know Java Reflection code
try to get some system level instance
through reflection currently we don't
really enforce that serly uh you know in
theory that we can uh we can try to
enforce this level of security by some
um access rules or the different class
loaders for you know for system versus
uh user space uh to enforce that but
that that is a good question we're still
working on this right yes and it's
important to point out too that because
you can use Kafka right out the box
Kafka itself provides no security for
those topics so therefore by extension
samza doesn't as well so what should
people be doing to ensure that their
streaming code is secure do you have any
tips or suggestions so don't don't do
reflection right don't do reflection and
uh always going through the send system
API code to interact with the system and
then um including the io system the uh
State stce and then coordination system
right and are there validations within
that API themselves or
what kind of guarantees does the you're
saying if the Sam API is the safest way
what kind of guarantees does that API
provide that helps to uh ensure security
you mean does the Sens API self uh
validate whether there's invalid access
to that right so the apis themselves
have certain type signatures for each
function that you're using I'm assuming
that there are security there's security
layer baked into all those functions I
don't think there is currently got it
and so then
what what benefit are you drawing from
ensuring that you properly use that API
then so the if you properly use set of
API then the Cod pass is all controlled
by a platform that we actually as a
sensor Community member that we does not
really you know go underneath the uh go
underneath the sking of certain objects
and you know uh manipulate with the
system uh unauthorized system objects by
default okay so it's more for debugging
or for you know if someone posts a bug
to the Apache project they can say well
I use XYZ apis and then there's some
sort of guarantees around trying to fix
that because it's part of the you're
going through the ecosystem then rather
than going around it yeah because
underneath this set of apis then no USIC
code it's all platform code got it okay
great so this is this is a very helpful
introduction to the to the whole
ecosystem for samza one really
interesting thing I noticed about Apache
General is it seems to own the streaming
space overall and there are a lot of
tools for streaming in the Apache
ecosystem so I'd love to take a little
bit of a detour and talk more about each
of those and see where samza fits into
the overall landscape of streaming sure
so uh we've already talked about Kafka
Kafka itself is a streaming uh framework
that you could use on its own so while
samza allows you to plug into Kafka
Kafka you don't necessarily need to plug
samza into
right so Kafka itself if you needed to
handle streaming of data you could use
that Standalone spark is another one
what instance would I want to use spark
for so if you're are talking spark so
spark historically spark implement the
streaming in a micro bway right so only
I think only after 24 or 25 the uh Spar
structure streaming is kind of a
reinvented the whole API so that from
API point of view you don't see the
microbatch anymore but underneath
there's the execution environment for
the spark structure streaming is still
either microbatch or or there's another
way called continuous execution right
and you have to switch between them the
microbatch is well adopted U spark way
of doing the streaming and the
continuous execution is not yet popular
yet right and uh for C so that's that
that's the uh the spark side thing so if
you compare uh Sansa with spark then sza
is a pure streaming engine so the
comparison with the microb batches with
the pure streaming you can do uh event
by event stream processing and async
commit uh with each of the events right
and with a micro batch you always need
to synchronize on the batch boundary and
your chop your checkpoint is also need
to um synchronize with the batch
boundaries right so in you know in a lot
of use cases that it's not convenient
right so that's the short comparison
between sza and the spark there uh you
know um for the comparison between sza
and the kfka stream actually is an
interesting story that kka stream is
literally a forof FR Sensa the reason
being okay at at the early discussion in
the S Community there are two different
scoups schools of thinkings that a since
kfka is already a you popular product
and then there are tons of need that
okay uh for small media use cases I do
not really want to uh stand up on my own
yarn cluster my zookeeper so I want to
have you know Standalone or as a library
as stream processing as a library as my
primary use case but on the other end um
for uh for example for the logic
Department like uh LinkedIn and at that
time Netflix and other big installment
having each of the different teams who
develop the stream processing pipelines
to run their own uh hardware and having
a you know many many repeated SRE and
operational effort to monitor those 24
by7 jobs uh across a company is
definitely not uh the way to go so uh
there's a there's also a strong need to
keep the
hosted and uh you know running stream
processing as a service as the um you
know primary uh offering in the uh in
the in the S community so not that that
said not saying that we are not um you
know U as a s committee we don't do not
recognize the Standalone uh you know
Standalone um way of uh deploying things
uh just the priority wise uh that's
different so um literally at that time
then uh Kafka wants a first party the uh
you know serving the small media use
cases so they spin off the Standalone
faster and uh it took us some while to
get to the due uh coordination mode that
implementing the Standalone send the
Standalone with zuker but that's the
main difference like even it look at a
cfast stream as for today um it is still
as a as a library model it doesn't
really provide you know as a service
okay so if I'm understanding you
correctly you'd want to use Kafka stream
for these small to medium instances
because it's all baked in together for
it's just an easier use case whereas if
you really want to use the full to the
full extent you'd want to integrate
Kafka with samza so these these larger
customers are going to be using the
distinct yep Kafka for it its use samza
for its use between the streaming and
the processing portions but for these
smaller use cases they're going to go
with
Kafka stream built into Kafka yeah I
think it's uh to me is exchangeable for
uh for the smaller media cases uh
between K stream and a s Standalone is
kind of exchangeable Kafka stream may
have a little bit lighter weed in terms
of okay zuker set up and those things
yeah got it but LinkedIn themselves is
using the full LinkedIn both actually oh
you use both and what so what instances
internally are you using Kream for
versus is no no no not not Cas Fram
LinkedIn use bow sends us uh yarn and
Standalone right yeah right got it okay
that makes sense so there's def I mean
there's way more than just those two so
we've we've covered spark which is
definitely more in the sort of cluster
Computing big data analytics we've got
Kream which is another sort of
Standalone service that's more
integrated into Kafka and it sounds like
spark then just just to wrapping up that
piece spark is probably used before you
would want to use something like samza
even your using batching as a batching
is definitely something you're going to
be trying out before you're trying out a
processing framework so do you find a
lot of people coming from spark and then
trying out uh samza or is it just
different use cases in general so uh in
the well in early days spark is and the
Sam you know spark and the stream side
um is kind of a mostly isolated silos
and people who write people who want to
write bad UPS use SP and then people who
want to use uh use the real time
analytics to write incenter right but uh
we've seen uh as as like since 2016 or
17 we've seen more and more use cases
once do both right and that's exactly
also our uh journey toward okay uh try
to get a convergence API between the
batch word and then the the stream word
and so far our strategies we actually
discover in the year of 2016 and the
later
2017 beam is a uh you know good choice
for us because beam API is stressing for
basically putting a lot of um Rich
stream process semantics and the syntax
on the API but the whole API layer is
engine agnostic so the the the beams you
know tecture is okay there's a API layer
describing all the user logic uh what
you want to do with the uh with the
stream processing but underneath you can
have different Runners which is AD
damper to translate user logic to a
particular engine for example spark can
be an engineer sensor can be an engine
there Flint can be an engineer and even
there are more like Apex and others
right so we feel that is a best fit for
our strategy because okay there uh if
you compare the different um you know
different engines in uh in LinkedIn that
spark has tons of optimization for
throughput and uh integrated well with
the the batch ecosystem stream side uh
sensor has its own uh tons of
optimization in WR time and integration
with the uh nearline and online
ecosystem in LinkedIn so there's a huge
gap if you want to replace one versus
the other yet you probably need to spend
a years of effort to replicate the uh
optimizations you done the on the other
side but with beam since the beam
application uh beam layer allows the
user to just uh you know focus it on the
uh application logic then the
optimization and also how do you run the
same logic on stream versus batch
environments becomes you know kind of a
hidden layer from the user right so that
that's uh that allow us to have you know
kind of a more ADV quicker integration
for the convergence use cases and allows
to uh Advance on the uh you know uh uh
optimizations for each different
different um engines separately and this
beam are you're talking about is this
the same one that powers erlang and
elixir the concurrency languages no the
beam is Apache beam which is I think is
a a project started in 2016 and right
now is becomes the uh top level apach
project already yeah there are just the
more I sort of unpacking this the more
you can see that there aache really has
so many services that power this whole
streaming space and you also mentioned
Flink earlier which is more for
distributed data flow or parallelization
so that sounds like it's another system
yet again where it's not about
necessarily replacing one thing with the
other but it's about complimenting each
other through this beam layer that
that's a thing that if I want if I want
to say a short comparison
with you know with the landscape um I
usually categorize in four different
aspects right so um talking about all
the all the you know uh different um
stateof art platforms and engines out
there uh one aspect is whether the API
is pure streaming versus microbatch so
you can see that FR and sza actually is
mostly uh pure streaming because it you
know usually the API is event by event
processing allows acing commit features
and those things and dataow which Google
data FR and the spark structur streaming
mostly operated on the microbatch mode
but then that's the API layer layer of
difference the implementation
architecture layer of difference is okay
there are IPC versus shuun cues uh in
the in the um whole pipeline so that's a
know if you compare all the different
systems it's very unique like um for sza
uh Flame data frow and Spar structure
streaming in a single job pipeline they
all use RPC between the stages of a
single pipeline which has to be started
on timeout when the communication
between the operators in different
stages have issues right from the
Upstream Downstream sensor you know
implements a different way that uh it
leverages the C car Q as an intermediate
shuffling uh shuffling Cube so instead
of IPC so if uh if you have intermediate
you know uh stage one produce something
stage two continue process this output
from stage one uh it is all communicated
through a c Cube so uh it has advantages
of okay you isolate the uh failures in
the downstream from the upstream and you
guarantee the orders of all the
sequences that once you once you
materialize once of all the events you
want to process the downstream will all
be see the same sequence there the
downside of course is you know uh added
some added some latency and also added
some prision cost in the whole parip
right that's the second aspect the third
aspect is okay the large state store
supports so if you if you compare all
these then um Flink and sza actually um
comes with very comparable feature sets
that it all comes with the native free
offering of roxb based local store for
lar States spark structure streaming by
default offers okay hdfs based state
store if you say if you write a map with
a state uh operator in spark right the
issue is that as as quoted from date
breaks offering on Zer the free state
store implementation hdfs has some
performance issues when the size of each
state goes beyond a certain um certain
size I forgot exact number but I think
it's a in the gigabyte range then in
that case you will have to purchase the
rock D based state store for this for
the larest state store from data braks
as a proprietary offering right so
that's that's a that's a difference
right okay the um whether you know for
Flink and for uh for SVA that by free
you get the state store uh of you know
larg state store support uh with The
Rock and in spart you need to pay money
right and then last last aspect I was
thinking is you know to compare all
those is a cloud integration right
whether you have a native integration
with the uh public vendor as a service
so on that front actually uh cloud data
FL and the spark streaming uh has a
better integration as they all you know
cloudro is a native offering from Google
spot streaming has the U offering
basically the first class uh service
offering from azour uh Flink and Sans
are mostly are freelancer so you can
just run your own cluster run your own
service by yourself but as for now
there's no Cloud vendor based offering
for that yet hopefully that that's
giving a you know overall comparison
that I have right yeah and you know
there's yet another project that I think
stitches some of them together one of
the topics you mentioned that's a big
differentiator between the different
Services is whether you're focusing on
batching versus pure streaming Apache
Apex is yet another streaming tool
that's mostly around processing either
streams or batches uh so it sounds like
if you're you had mentioned this earlier
with uh with Kafka that if you if you
have spark you you could complement
spark with samza one handles the micro
batching and one handles the streaming
it sounds like Apex could be that meta
processor that's allowing either streams
or batches to to complete like through
this system how would you use Apex in
that sense so Apex itself is an engine
so I I don't think Apex itself is API
layer what I was uh uh mentioned earlier
is Apache beam is an API layer so it
doesn't really Demands a specific engine
to run beneath and Apex I think is a it
has a beam Runner basically it runs the
beam program uh as an engine but itself
is not it it is a designed as a
convergence engine but I don't uh I
don't think it's self you can swap in
any um engines beneath that okay yeah so
in that sense if you didn't want to use
beam you Apex could run the whole thing
for you because it's it is itself the
engine that's powering this yeah you can
you can choose to all in for Apex but
unfortunately I I don't think the
project is currently very very active
and they it also comes uh way later than
uh what we have the amount on and we
have to back got it okay and then so
then to sort of rounding the quarter
here in Apache streaming projects the
one that actually sounded most similar
to me you had mentioned that there's a
lot of similarity in pure streaming
between Flink and samza but I also
noticed storm sounded very similar as
well too because that handles stream
processing computation so i' would
imagine that there's a lot of overlap
with how cor s processes the jobs well
the containers that are in those jobs
right so it sounds like you might
actually have to look at comparisons
storm was an earlier competitive with s
that we analyze I think there are few uh
disadvantages we see in storm that at
the moment you know uh stop us from
investigating that one is storms uh
large topology management like the uh
the Nimbus based large topology
management is not quite reliable at the
time that often causes uh stalling of
the pipelines and then the other is okay
a storm do really come with a good large
state store support with short latencies
right so even for that for that you know
for that aspect in fact sza it was the
first one integr with the rock DB by
native um by native first class support
uh Flink actually works with the
inmemory state stor offering first then
it comes with a a full law with rock
implementation storm St doesn't really
have that at the moment okay so you so
at this point then storm is not
something that people are actually
actively trying to compare if you're
going to choose something in the
competition space you're going to be
choosing samza you're not going to have
to worry about storm at this point
anymore yeah so for uh from for us I
think um in my opinion the most uh
currently if I'm looking at okay what
are the top competitors in this space um
I'm I'm going to be looking at uh Flink
and then SPX scure streaming um uh a
Flink is in a lot of sense that the
functional wise offered uh feature-wise
is very close to what SanSai is offering
spark structure streaming the main
reason is spark has a big ecosystem
fromont the batch side right so then how
do I know which framework to choose if
there's so many to evaluate what am I
actually looking for in particular
pieces to help me choose the right
system for me right so that's that's
um from our point of view then um we
always stress for performance right so I
can I cannot really um I think it's hard
to come up with a general rules or
reasons for people who want to choose a
versus B I can explain several reasons
why Sansa is adopted as a mainst stream
processing engine in LinkedIn right so
from the LinkedIn uh prospective point
of view so the first reason performance
so uh SAS kka interface is is thus far
the most advanced IO connector on Kafka
among all the stream processing
platforms that I'm see if you look at
most of the stream processing platforms
integration with Kafka is saying okay
each topic or each topic partition you
have to have a consumer instance for
that right so then um this Kafka this C
instance will U feed for a uh for a uh
task in a you know in one of uh in in a
task for processing this uh the in order
sequence coming from a petition um but
then um if you uh if you're uh consuming
from many different topic petitions one
disadvantage we've seen is some of the
you know some of the platforms that
basically need to instantiate multiple
Kaa consumer instances in the same
container to consume multiple different
Kafka topics uh and topic partitions
from that and in order to having a one
to one maping front okay there's one in
one input sequence there's one threat
processing that it works with two
conditions a if the input topic partion
is relatively static set and B the
number of total of memory footprint of
all this uh number of uh top partions
sorry including all those number of uh
consumer instance in a single process is
not high pressure but um s Works in uh
in more advanced way that we actually
instantiate a single consumer instance
for the uh for the kfka cluster even you
have consume from even you're consuming
from 10 or even 100 of a topic partions
from this cluster and then internally
there's a multipler and also a per par F
control mechanism that we can we see
okay the uh there's a the this multier
will take the messages from all the top
appications send out to different thread
that is working on different um
different uh you know uh partitions and
if one of the thread is going slow we
just pause on this particular input
partition which which doesn't really
pass the whole consumer instance a lot
of other system will do right so that's
that allows us to shrink you know um
kind of uh doing a very dense
consumption model in a single consumer
instance yet to maintain a high
throughput in terms of you know it needs
to F out to multiple paradism that gives
a a lot of a benefit in terms of like
performance for sensor processing uh the
other the other uh advantage of course
the uh the integration with Native
integration of Rox DB as a local
embedded store and which it yields the
submillisecond read right latency and
the strong synchronized the read after
right semantic consistency in the state
store reite we had an earlier
performance benchmark show that Sansa
supports uh 1.2 million requests per
second on a single host uh in a very old
host with only like a one gig Nick right
you know uh we have we have no reason to
you know no reason to um not believe in
that it can scale up with the modern
Hardwares with you 10 gig Nicks and
other beier um uh CPU and memory that's
a that that's the one big aspect of
LinkedIn choosing sensor right there
also uh LinkedIn reason for TR s also is
okay the uh with the improved apis with
reach wiing semantics so that is coming
from two aspects in in terms of the API
improvements since
2016 a we started supporting C so C
supports allows many users uh such as
data scientists or AI Engineers to write
the um stream processing pipeline
without
understanding underneath system details
and B is we are integr with beam API s
the beam Runner is the one that we uh
built since 2016 which allows us to
leverage the rich semantics of be API
specifically winding and event time and
also there there's you know triggers
which H is a very Advanced API and
Concepts in the Stream processing you
can read you know uh Taylor aido stream
process processing 101 stream processing
102 to understand what is a trigger and
late arrival and early arrival means
right this will this also allows us to
support multilanguage support from beam
which recent you know uh we have
successfully Advanced to support python
stream processing applications in
LinkedIn right so that's that's the um
that's the API side those are all built
on top of a again those are all built on
top of a high level API in sensor which
allows you specify the mul stage
pipelines in a single uh application
execution T there's not much of a work
that is still going on with CQ and B uh
the third aspect that you know uh I want
to mention is we have actually improved
on the operability at a scale for stream
processing um sensor quite a bit so the
biggest challenge of course in stream
processing is maintaining a large number
of stream processing pipelines with
strict slas
24/7 we have actually uh a lot of effort
in uh you know uh in many aspects of
that uh I I will only mention two here
one is we actually added Advanced Autos
skan capabilities in Sor platform one of
the biggest complaints of course from
our users is okay the complexity
difficulty and tuning the configuration
of a front uh of a running pipeline the
incoming traffic fluctuates and when you
deploy the uh deploy the same pipeline
from data center a to data center B the
traffic difference and then the hardware
may be different so there's T of the
tuning you have down in data center a
doesn't work for this andb this is a
nuance and uh a lot of creates a lot of
pains uh from the user this is
especially true for CQ users since CQ
users mostly are not familiar with the
operational details of physical system
so we since has put a lot of effort in
providing tools and system to help
monitoring and aut skills jobs so our
users won't need to carry the
operational overhead we our recent
success in this effort um you can find
it in a paper in hot cow 20 the title is
autos skining for stream processing
application and Linkedin we actually
deployed the Autos skinning system
together with our you know uh our
logistical operation pipeline in
LinkedIn and uh uh achieved the great um
performance and also oper
cost uh savings and we we we view it as
an important differentiator of our
technology the second aspect I want to
mention in this oper operability
Improvement is the lar estate failure
recovery and resilience so as I
explained earlier sza leverage Rock DB
for local States and Flink follows and
even uh Spar structured streaming when
you need to have a log States it also
provides the Rock DBS the local storage
it provides the fast access to the uh in
in the healthy state of the job but sza
uses CFA topic as a change lock to
recover the state store in failure and
this is heavily tuned toward uh the uh
Healthy High in wrong time but the
recovery from the kafa topic is
relatively slow so we actually
implemented uh two solutions to fasten
the state recovery already one is host
Affinity in yarn so
we allow the uh job to schedule the
container back to the same host in yarn
if the host is still available then we
can leverage whatever the local snapshot
that is that exist on the yarn uh yarn
uh host and uh fasten the recovery this
actually in production achieves 50 times
or 20 times faster recovery and the
other is U to battle against the case
that the host is totally gone so it's
called hot standby container we have
implemented a way that you can stand up
hot standby container in another host
which keeps the state in sync and
immediately take over the work from the
failed container if the mission is
critical um that is uh that is a um
allowing us to operate in the range that
for Bion critical jobs that you cannot
really suffer any downtime there there
are Works still in progress to improve
the state recovery uh in case of host
failes going on um try to uh strike a
balance between okay the the cost you
pay in having many standby host uh
standby containers versus uh the time
you uh you take to recover so that's the
uh third aspect of that and just want to
uh you know this this is a set of uh uh
reasons that we trose sens as the WR
time platform in LinkedIn right uh there
are examples of the S users like eBay
refin uh Trip Advisor optim optimizely
which is a markeet Analysis company
slack and those uh those companies all I
think most of the use Cas choose is send
because of the above reason great and
we'll link to all this documentation on
the show notes so you'll be able to see
the samza official website the Twitter
the uh link to other resources at
awesome streaming as well as the uh
paper you referenced earlier Auto
scaling for stream processing and
Linkedin um so we're basically going to
wrap things up e could you just
summarize really quick you know when
someone's ready to make the dive into
samza what kind of things you know what
sort of parting advice could you give to
folks if they're looking to get started
with streaming stream processing or
samza in general um so I think first of
all so when you are looking uh when
you're looking into a stream process
platform of course I think you need to
understand okay in this domain the
usually okay the throughput fast uh
performance and um you know uh
consistency is a big trade-off so you
know just keep in mind that in any
distributed um streaming platform that
um you may need to pay you know you need
to uh you look for those trade-offs
between that and um if you're
specifically looking for comparison
between s uh between the stream
processing uh platforms I think um as I
mentioned earlier then API one you know
the four aspects I will recommend is you
know look at API see whether it's pure
screaming or micro batch and you know
look at look back to your use case
whether you can take the uh batch way uh
micro batch way of writing your logic or
uh you have to do a Fel stream way
because there are some um there's some
logic is hard to align the logic with
the batch boundary for example the
session windows and all the things right
and then the other the other is about
the the other aspect is okay for the
whole pipeline that do you um uh do how
much of a consistent regarding to okay
atomicity or not atomicity but most of
the snapshot consistent snapshot or
exact ones you want to achieve if you
want a strong uh exact ones um across
the whole pipeline then uh you may pay
the additional cost of synchronization
of the state in different stages which
obious is probably give you a better uh
option here but if you are um you know
going with okay I do not want to sacrify
my performance because of that I want to
have a you know eventual consistent way
and U being able to isolate different
state of failures um in uh without uh
with without impacting other then a
persistent shuffering que may help to
solve your problem in you know in
between the stages of a pipeline the
size of state store is another big
problem if you're doing a um stateful uh
state for stream processing then uh I I
would recommend that if you if the size
is uh big then um look for a rock TV
solution yeah mostly is that and lastly
the uh on the cloud vendor integration
site then it is up to your appetite of
okay do you want to you know have your
own installation and um have to run a
student processing cluster or you can
leverage some existing um Cloud vendor
offerings that's just a star with there
are a lot more details to um you know to
evaluate perfect well e we just about
out of time thank you so much for coming
on software engineering radio today no
problem thank you a lot
Adam thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se- radio.com net to
provide feedback you can comment on each
episode on the website or reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack Channel at seo. slack.com you can
also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SE
radio is licensed under creative comons
license
2.5 thanks for listening